Having spent 18 years as a child of the state
بعد قضاء 18 عاما كطفل بالولايات المتحدة
in children's homes and foster care,
في منازل الرعاية والحضانة،
you could say that I'm an expert on the subject,
يمكن القول أني خبير في الموضوع،
and in being an expert, I want to let you know that
وكوني أصبحت خبيراً، أريد أن أخبركم أن
being an expert does in no way make you right
كونك خبير لا يعني بأي طريقة أنك على حق
in light of the truth.
في نورالحقيقة
If you're in care, legally the government is your
لو كنت في الرعاية، يعني قانونياً أن الحكومه هي
parent, loco parentis.
والديك، ولي أمرك.
Margaret Thatcher was my mother. (Laughter)
مارقريت ثاتشر كانت أمي. (ضحك)
Let's not talk about breastfeeding. (Laughter)
دعونا لانتحدث عن الرضاعة الطبيعية. (ضحك)
Harry Potter was a foster child.
هاري بوتر كان طفل بالتبني.
Pip from "Great Expectations" was adopted;
بيب من "Great Expectations" كان متبنّى:
Superman was a foster child;
سوبر مان كان طفل بالتبني
Cinderella was a foster child;
سندريلا كانت طفله بالتبني
Lisbeth Salander, the girl with the dragon tattoo,
لزبيث سالاندر، الفتاة ذات وشم التنين،
was fostered and institutionalized;
كانت طفلة بالتبني و تحت رعاية مؤسسة
Batman was orphaned;
باتمان كان ميتّم
Lyra Belacqua from Philip Pullman's "Northern Lights"
ليرا بيلاكوا من فليب بولمان "أضواء الشمال"
was fostered;
كانت طفلة بالتبني
Jane Eyre, adopted;
جين إير, متبناة
Roald Dahl's James from "James and the Giant Peach;"
رولد دايلس جيمس من "جيمس والخوخ العملاق"
Matilda; Moses -- Moses! (Laughter)
ماتيلدا، موسى - موسى! (ضحك)
Moses! (Laughter) --
موسى! (ضحك)
the boys in Michael Morpurgo's "Friend or Foe;"
الأولاد في مايكل موربورغو "صديق أم عدو"
Alem in Benjamin Zephaniah's "Refugee Boy;"
اليم في بينجامين زيفانيا "الولد اللّاجيء"
Luke Skywalker --
لوك سكاي ووكر
Luke Skywalker! (Laughter) --
لوك سكاي ووكر! (ضحك)
Oliver Twist;
أوليفر تويست
Cassia in "The Concubine of Shanghai" by Hong Ying;
كاسي في "المحظيه من شنغهاي" من قبل هونغ يينغ؛
Celie in Alice Walker's "The Color Purple."
سيلي في اليس ووكر "لون البنفسج"
All of these great fictional characters, all of them
جميع هذة الشخصيات الخيالية الكبيرة، جميعهم
who were hurt by their condition,
الذين تألموا من قبل ظروفهم
all of them who spawned thousands of other books
جميعهم الذين أنتجوا آلاف من الكتب الأخرى
and other films, all of them
وأفلام أخرى, جميعهم
were fostered, adopted or orphaned.
كانوا أطفال حضانة، متبنون، أو ميتّمون
It seems that writers know that the child
كان الكُتاب يعرفون أنّ الطفل
outside of family reflects on what family truly is
خارج الأسرة يعكس ماهية الأسرة الحقيقية
more than what it promotes itself to be.
أكثر مما يحاول عكسه غير ذلك.
That is, they also use extraordinary skills
أيضاً يستخدمون مهارات استثنائية
to deal with extraordinary situations on a daily basis.
للتعامل مع الحالات الإستثنائية في حياتهم اليومية
How have we not made the connection?
كيف لم نستطيع فهم الرابط؟
And why have we not made the connection, between
لماذا لم نفهم الرابط بين
— How has that happened? —
كيف حدث ذلك؟
between these incredible characters of popular culture
بين هذه الشخصيات المدهشة في الثقافة الشعبية
and religions, and the fostered, adopted or orphaned child
والأديان و بين أطفال الحضانة والتبني و اليتامى
in our midst? It's not our pity that they need.
في وسطنا؟ ليست الشفقة ما يحتاجون
It's our respect.
بل إنه احترامنا
I know famous musicians,
أعرف موسيقيين معروفين،
I know actors and film stars and millionaires and novelists
أعرف ممثلين ونجوم سينما ومليونيرات وروائيين
and top lawyers and television executives
ومحاميين كبار ومنفذين بالتلفاز
and magazine editors and national journalists
ومحررين مجلات وصحفيين عالميين
and dustbinmen and hairdressers, all who were
وعمال نظافة و مصففين شعر، الجميع ممن
looked after children, fostered, adopted or orphaned,
كان بدار حضانة، متبنين أو ميتّمون،
and many of them grow into their adult lives
وكثيرون منهم كبروا إلى سن الرشد
in fear of speaking of their background, as if it may
وهم يخافون أن يتحدثون عن خلفيتهم، كأنها
somehow weaken their standing in the foreground,
بطريقة ما تضعف موقفهم في المقدمة
as if it were somehow Kryptonite, as if it were a time bomb
أو كما لو كانت ب كريبتونيت "نقطة ضعف لشخصية سوبرمان"، أو كانت قنبلة موقوتة
strapped on the inside. Children in care,
مربوطة من الداخل. الأطفال في الرعاية
who've had a life in care, deserve the right
الذين كانت لهم حياة في الرعاية، لديهم الحق
to own and live the memory of their own childhood.
أن يعيشون ويتمسكون بذكريات طفولتهم
It is that simple.
بتلك البساطة
My own mother — and I should say this here —
والدتي أنا ــــ وينبغي أن أقول هذا هنا ـــ
she same to this country in the late '60s,
أتت إلى هذه البلد في أواخر الـستينات،
and she was, you know, she found herself pregnant,
وكما تعرفون، وجدت نفسها حامل
as women did in the late '60s. You know what I mean?
كما تعرفون النساء في الستينات، تعرفون ما أعني؟
They found themselves pregnant.
وجدوا أنفسهم حوامل
And she sort of, she had no idea of the context
لم يكن لها فكره عن السياق
in which she'd landed.
التي وجدت نفسها عليها
In the 1960s -- I should give you some context -- in the 1960s,
في 1960 سأعطيكم السياق في الستينات
if you were pregnant and you were single,
لو كنت حامل وأنتي عزباء
you were seen as a threat to the community.
يراك الجميع بأنك تهديد للمجتمع
You were separated from your family by the state.
يتم فصلك من عائلتك من قبل الدولة
You were separated from your family and placed into
يتم فصلك من عائلتك ووضعك في
mother and baby homes.
منازل الأمهات والأطفال
You were appointed a social worker.
وسيُختار لك راعية اجتماعية
The adoptive parents were lined up.
تجد وقتها أباء التبني في صف طويل
It was the primary purpose of the social worker, the aim,
وهو السبب الرئيسي لتواجد الراعية الاجتماعية،
to get the woman at her most vulnerable time
للحصول على امراة في أشد أوقاتها ضعفاً
in her entire life, to sign the adoption papers.
في حياتها كلها، لتوقع على أوراق التبني.
So the adoption papers were signed.
إذا أوراق التبني تم توقيعها
The mother and baby's homes were often run by nuns.
غالبا ماتكون منازل الأمهات والأطفال منظمة من قبل الراهبات
The adoption papers were signed,
تم التوقيع على اوراق التبني
the child was given to the adoptive parents, and the mother
تم اعطاء الطفل إلى والوالدين بالتبني, والأم
shipped back to her community
يتم إعادتها مرة أخرى إلى مجتمعها
to say that she'd been on a little break.
ليقال إنها كانت في استراحة قصيرة
A little break.
استراحة قصيرة
The first secret of shame for a woman
السر الأول من العار على المرأة
for being a woman, "a little break."
هو أن تكون في "استراحة قصيرة"
The adoption process took, like, a matter of months,
تأخذ اجراءت التبني، مسألة شهور
so it was a closed shop, you know, sealed deal,
إذا إنها كمتجر مغلق, كما تعلمون والاتفاق المختوم
an industrious, utilitarian solution:
صناعة، حل منفعي
the government, the farmer,
الحكومة، المزارع
the adopting parents, the consumer,
آباء التبني هم المستهلك
the mother, the earth, and the child, the crop.
الأم هي الأرض، والطفل هوالمحصول
It's kind of easy to patronize the past,
من السهل ان نستامح مع الماضي
to forego our responsibilities in the present.
لنتخلى عن مسؤلياتنا في الحاضر
What happened then is a direct reflection
ماذا حدث عندها إنه الإنعكاس المباشر
of what is happening now. Everybody believed themselves
لما يحدث الان. الكل يصدق نفسه
to be doing the right thing by God and by the state
انهم يفعلون الشيء الصحيح من قبل الله والدولة.
for the big society, fast-tracking adoption.
للمجتمع الكبير، في مسار التبني السريع.
So anyway, she comes here, 1967, she's pregnant,
على كل حال، هي اتت الى هنا عام 1967 وهي حامل،
and she comes from Ethiopia that was celebrating
وقد أتت من أثيوبيا والتي كانت تحتفل
its own jubilee at the time
باليوبيل الخاص بها وقتها
under the Emperor Haile Selassie,
تحت الامبراطور هيلا سيلاسي،
and she lands months before the Enoch Powell speech,
أتت قبل أشهر من خطاب اينوك باويل
the "Rivers of Blood" speech.
خطاب "أنهار الدماء"
She lands months before the Beatles release "The White Album,"
وصلت قبل شهور قبل أن يصدروا البيتل "الالبوم الابيض"
months before Martin Luther King was killed.
بشهور قبل قتل مارتن لوثر كينج
It was a summer of love if you were white.
كان صيف الحب لو كنت ابيض
If you were black, it was a summer of hate.
ولو كنت أسود فكان صيف الكره
So she goes from Oxford, she's sent to the north of England
ذهبت من اوكسفورد و أُرسلت إلى شمال بريطانيا
to a mother and baby home, and appointed a social worker.
إلى بيت الأمهات والأطفال وعين لها عاملة اجتماعية
It's her plan. You know, I have to say this in the Houses --
كانت خطتها. تعرفون لابد ان اقول هذا في المنازل
It's her plan to have me fostered for a short period of time
كانت خطتها أن أكون في الرعاية لفترة بسيطة
while she studies. But the social worker,
في حين تدرس، ولكن الراعية الاجتماعية،
he had a different agenda.
كان لديها خطة مختلفة
He found the foster parents, and he said to them,
وجدت اباء الرعاية وأخبرتهم
"Treat this as an adoption. He's yours forever.
"عاملوه كأنه ابن متبنى". هو ملككم للأبد
His name is Norman." (Laughter)
اسمه نورمان" (ضحك)
Norman! (Laughter)
نورمان! (ضحك)
Norman!
نورمان!
So they took me. I was a message, they said.
لذا أخذوني. قالوا أني رسالة، هذا ما قالوا
I was a sign from God, they said.
إشارة من الرب، قالوا
I was Norman Mark Greenwood.
كنت نورمان مارك قرين وود.
Now, for the next 11 years, all I know is that this woman,
الآن للـ 11 عام الآتية، كل ما اعرفه تلك المرأة،
this birth woman, should have her eyes scratched out
امرأة الولادة. يجب أن تخدش عينيها
for not signing the adoption papers. She was an evil woman
لعدم توقيعها على أوراق التبني. كانت امرأة شريرة
too selfish to sign, so I spent those 11 years
أنانية جداً لتوقع، فقضيت الـ 11 عام
kneeling and praying.
أركع و أصلي
I tried praying. I swear I tried praying.
حاولت الصلاة، أحلف أني حاولت الصلاة
"God, can I have a bike for Christmas?"
"يارب، هل من يمكنني الحصول على دراجة للكريسماس؟"
But I would always answer myself, "Yes, of course you can."
لكن دائما ما أجيب على نفسي، "نعم، بالطبع يمكنك"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then I was supposed to determine whether that
بعدها كان علي أن أحدد ما اذا كان
was the voice of God or it was the voice of the Devil.
ذلك الصوت، نداء من الله أم الشيطان
And it turns out I've got the Devil inside of me.
وفي النهاية اتضح أن الشيطان كان بداخلي
Who knew? (Laughter)
من كان يعرف؟ (ضحك)
So anyway, two years sort of passed,
على كل حال، مرت سنتين بطريقة ما
and they had a child of their own,
ورزقوا بابن من صلبهم
and then another two years passed, and they had another child of their own,
وبعد مرور سنتين، رزقوا بابن آخر من صلبهم
and then another time passed
ومرت الأيام
and they had another child that they called an accident,
ورزقوا باخر، والذي يدعونه بحادث مفاجئ
which I thought was an unusual name. (Laughter)
والذي اعتقدت أنه اسم غير معتاد (ضحك)
And I was on the cusp of, sort of, adolescence,
وكنت على حافة المراهقة بطريقة ما
so I was starting to take biscuits from the tin without asking.
كنت اخذ البسكويت من القصدير دون استأذان
I was starting to stay out a little bit late, etc., etc.
وبدأت بالسهر الى وقت متأخر من الليل، الخ.، الخ
Now, in their religiosity, in their naivete,
الآن، في تدينهم، في سذاجتهم،
my mom and dad, which I believed them to be forever,
أمي و أبي، الذين آمنت أنهم سيكونون كذلك للأبد
as they said they were, my mom and dad
كما قالوا أنهما، أمي وأبي
conceived that I had the Devil inside of me.
تصوروا أن الشيطان في داخلي
And what -- I should say this here, because this is how
وماذا--ينبغي أن أقول هنا، لأن هكذا
they engineered my leaving.
صمموا خطة إخراجي
They sat me at a table, my foster mom, and she said to me,
أجلساني على الطاولة وقالت لي أمي بالتبني
"You don't love us, do you?" At 11 years old.
"انت لا تحبنا اليس كذلك؟ " في عمر 11 سنة
They've had three other children. I'm the fourth. The third was an accident.
كان لديهم ثلاثة أطفال آخرين. أنا الرابع. والثالث كان حادثا
And I said, "Yeah, of course I do." Because you do.
فقلت، "بالطبع أنا أحبكم" لأنك تحبهم
My foster mother asked me to go away to think about love
أمي بالتبني طلبت مني ان أذهب وأفكر في موضوع الحب
and what it is and to read the Scriptures and to come back tomorrow
وماهو وأن اقرأ الكتاب وأعود غداً
and give my most honest and truthful answer.
وأعطي إجابتي الأكثر صدقا ومصداقية
So this was an opportunity. If they were asking me
لذا فقد كانت هذه فرصة. إذا كانا يسألاني
whether I loved them or not, then I mustn't love them,
ما إذا ماكنت أحبهم أم لا فهذا يعني أنه يجب أن لا أحبهم
which led me to the miracle of thought that I thought they wanted me to get to.
الأمر الذي أدى بي إلى معجزة الفكر الذي كانا يريدان مني
"I will ask God for forgiveness and His light will shine
"أسأل الله ان المغفرة وأن ينزل نوره
through me to them. How fantastic." This was an opportunity.
علي لاظهره عليهم، ما أروع هذا " كانت تلك فرصتي
The theology was perfect, the timing unquestionable,
اللاهوت كان متقن، التوقيت ليس به جدال،
and the answer as honest as a sinner could get.
والجواب نزيه مثل أكثر نزاهة يستطيع أن يصل لها مذنب
"I mustn't love you," I said to them. "But I will ask God for forgiveness."
أخبرتهم "لابد أن لا أحبكم. لكني سأسئل الله المغفرة"
"Because you don't love us, Norman,
"لأنك لا تحبنا، يا نورمان،
clearly you've chosen your path."
يتضح أنك اخترت طريقك"
Twenty-four hours later, my social worker,
بعد مرور 24 ساعة أخبرني الراعي الاجتماعي،
this strange man who used to visit me every couple of months,
هذا الرجل الغريب الذي كان يزوروني كل بضع شهور،
he's waiting for me in the car as I say goodbye to my parents.
كان ينتظرني في السيارة حال قولي لقاء سعيد لوالدي
I didn't say goodbye to anybody, not my mother, my father,
لم أودع أي شخص، حتى والدتي ووالدي،
my sisters, my brothers, my aunts, my uncles,
أخواتي، أخواني، عماتي، أعمامي،
my cousins, my grandparents, nobody.
أبناء أعمامي، أجدادي، لا أحد
On the way to the children's home, I started to ask myself,
في طريقي إلى منزل الأطفال، بدأت أسأل نفسي،
"What's happened to me?"
"ماذا حدث لي؟"
It's not that I'd had the rug pulled from beneath me
ليس ذلك أن البساط سحب من تحتي
as much as the entire floor had been taken away.
بل كأن كل الأرض اُخذت مني
When I got to the —
عندما وصلت الى ---
For the next four, five years,
الاربعة، الخمسة اعوام التالية،
I was held in four different children's homes.
كنت باربعة منازل أطفال مختلفة.
On the third children's home, at 15,
في بيت الأطفال الثالث، في الخامسة عشر،
I started to rebel, and what I did was,
بدأت في التمرد، ومافعلته هو
I got three tins of paint, Airfix paint that you use for models,
احضرت ثلاثة علب من الطلاء، الذي يستخدم للنماذج،
and I was -- it was a big children's home, big Victorian children's home --
وكنت في منزل الاطفال الكبير، منزل فيكتوري للأطفال كبير ---
and I was in a little turret at the top of it,
وكنت في برج على الجزء العلوي من المنزل
and I poured them, red, yellow and green,
سكبت الطلاء، أحمر، أصفر و أخضر،
the colors of Africa, down the tiles.
ألوان أفريقيا، في أسفل البلاط
You couldn't see it from the street, because the home
لا تستطيع رؤيته من الشارع، لأن المنزل
was surrounded by beech trees.
كان محاط بأشجار الزان
For doing this, I was incarcerated for a year
لأني قمت بذلك، تم سجني لعام
in an assessment center which was actually
في مركز التقييم، والذي في الحقيقة
a remand center. It was a virtual prison
كان مركز الحبس الاحتياطي. كان سجن ظاهري
for young people.
للشباب.
By the way, years later, my social worker said
بالمناسبة بعد مرور اعوام، الراعي الإجتماعي قال
that I should never have been put in there.
لم يكن ينبغي وضعي هناك.
I wasn't charged for anything. I hadn't done anything wrong.
لم توجه لي أي تهمة، لم أفعل أي شيء خاطئ
But because I had no family to inquire about me,
لكن لأني لم أملك أي أسرة تسأل عني
they could do anything to me.
يستطيعون أن يفعلون أي شيء بي
I'm 17 years old, and
أنا عمري 17 عام و
they had a padded cell.
كان لديهم زنزانة مبطنة
They would march me down corridors in last-size order.
كان يتركونني أتمشى تحت في آخر الممرات حسب ترتيبها في الحجم
They -- I was put in a dormitory
كانوا -- وضعوني في عنبر للنوم
with a confirmed Nazi sympathizer.
مع متعاطفين مع النازية
All of the staff were ex-police -- interesting --
كل العاملين كانوا شرطة سابقين --- مدهش---
and ex-probation officers.
ومراقبين سلوك.
The man who ran it was an ex-army officer.
المدير كان ضابط جيش سابق.
Every time I had a visit by a person who I did not know
كل مرة عندما يزورني شخص لا أعرفه
who would feed me grapes, once every three months,
ويعطيني عنب مره كل ثلاثة شهور،
I was strip-searched.
كان يجردونني للتفتيش.
That home was full of young boys who were on remand
ذلك المنزل كان مليء بأولاد في الحبس الاحتياطي
for things like murder.
لتُهم مثل القتل.
And this was the preparation that I was being given
وذلك كان التجهيز الذي أعطوني اياه
after 17 years as a child of the state.
بعد مرور 17 عام كطفل الدولة.
I have to tell this story.
لابد أن أحكي هذه القصة.
I have to tell it, because there was no one
كان لابد أن أحكيها لأنه لا يوجد شخص
to put two and two together.
لوضع الاثنين مع بعض.
I slowly became aware that I knew nobody
ببطء عرفت انني لا أعرف شخص
that knew me for longer than a year.
يعرفني لمدة أكثر من عام.
See, that's what family does.
هذا ما تفعله الأسرة.
It gives you reference points.
تعطيك نقاط للمرجع.
I'm not defining a good family from a bad family.
انني لا أعرّف الأسرة الجيدة من الأسرة السيئة.
I'm just saying that you know when your birthday is
إني أقول أنك تعرف متى عيد ميلادك
by virtue of the fact that somebody tells you when your birthday is,
بحُكم ان هناك شخص يخبرك متى عيد ميلادك،
a mother, a father, a sister, a brother, an aunt, an uncle,
أم، أب، اخت، أخ، عم، عمه،
a cousin, a grandparent. It matters to someone,
أبن عم، أجداد، تعني الكثير لشخص،
and therefore it matters to you. Understand,
وعليه يهمك الأمر. فهمت،
I was 14 years old, tucked away in myself, into myself,
كان عمري 14 عام، مختبي مع نفسي والى نفسي،
and I wasn't touched either, physically touched.
ولم يلمسني أحد، لمس جسدي.
I'm reporting back. I'm reporting back simply to say that
أنا أحكي عن هذا، أحكي عن هذا بكل بساطة لاقول
when I left the children's home I had two things
عندما تركت منزل الأطفال كان لدي شيئين
that I wanted to do. One was to find my family,
أريد أن افعلهم، الأول البحث عن أسرتي،
and the other was to write poetry.
والثاني أن أكتب قصيدة.
In creativity I saw light.
في الإبداع رأيت الضوء.
In the imagination I saw the endless possibility of life,
في الخيال رأيت إمكانية لا نهاية لها من الحياة،
the endless truth, the permanent creation of reality,
الحقيقة التي لا نهاية لها, وديمومة نشوء الواقع،
the place where anger was an expression
المكان الذي يكون الغضب فيه تعبيراً
in the search for love, a place where dysfunction
للبحث عن الحب، مكان الاختلال الوظيفي
is a true reaction to untruth.
كرد فعل لعدم الحقيقة
I've just got to say it to you all: I found all of my family
لابد أن أخبركم، أني وجدت كل أسرتي
in my adult life. I spent all of my adult life finding them,
عندما كبرت، قضيت كل حياتي في البحث عنهم،
and I've now got a fully dysfunctional family just like everybody else.
والآن لدي أسرة مختلة تماما مثل أي شخص آخر.
But I'm reporting back to you to say quite simply
ولكنني أحكيها مرة أخرى لكم لأقول بكل بساطة
that you can define how strong a democracy is
أنه يمكنكم تعريف الديمقراطية القوية
by how its government treats its child.
بكيفية معاملة حكومتها لطفلها.
I don't mean children. I mean the child of the state.
لا أعني الأطفال، أعني طفل الدولة.
Thanks very much. It's been an honor. (Applause)
شكراً جزيلاً. إنه شرف لي. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)